William Allan Neilson Personal Papers, 1852-1946 RG 32.02.personal
Smith College Archives
William Allan Neilson Personal Papers
1852-1946
Smith College Archives
Neilson, William Allan, 1869-1946.
RG 32.02
47 boxes (25 linear feet)
The Neilson Personal Papers include extensive family material. His letters to his brother and sisters are particularly valuable. Other letters present Neilson's view of life at Bryn Mawr College under M. Carey Thomas, his experiences tutoring Helen Keller at Radcliffe College, and his first impressions of Smith College. The also collection reflects his strong interest in liberal politics. Also included are writings of Elisabeth Muser Neilson and the Muser, Neilson and Allan family papers. Material relating to Margaret Farrard Thorp's 1956 biography, Neilson of Smith is included in the collection. Other materials includes correspondence, manuscripts, press releases, lecture notes, texts of speeches, and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
1869 Born in Doune, Perthshire, Scotland, March 28
1882-1886 Attended Montrose Academy
1886-1891 Studied at the University of Edinburgh, received M.A.
1891 Immigrated with family to Canada
1891-1895 Resident English Master, Upper Canada College, Toronto
1895-1898 Graduate work in English, Harvard University, M.A. (1897), Ph.D. (1898)
1898-1901 Associate Professor of English Literature, Bryn Mawr College
1901-1904 Instructor of English, Harvard University
1904-1906 Professor of English, Columbia University
1905 Became American citizen
1906-1917 Professor of English, Harvard University
1906 Married Elisabeth Muser in Offenburg, Germany, June 25
1914-1915 Exchange Professor, University of Paris
1917-1939 President of Smith College
1920-1946 Trustee, Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Education Served intermittently on the College Entrance Examination Board
1921 Initiated Special Honors program at Smith College
1924 President, Modern Language Association
1924-1945 Editorial Board of G.C. Merriam and Company
1925 Started Junior Year Abroad program at Smith College
1926-1946 Advisory Council, the Open Road, Inc.
1930-1946 Board of Directors, National Association for the Advancement of Colored People
1940-1941 Board of Directors, National Refugee Service
1940-1945 Chair, Executive Committee, Commission to Study the Organization of Peace
1941 Presided over the International Student Service Summer Student Leadership Institute at Campobello, New Brunswick
1942 Board of Overseers, Harvard University
1943 Chair,
1946 Died in Northampton, Massachusetts, February 13
1869 Born in Doune, Perthshire, Scotland, March 28
1882-1886 Attended Montrose Academy
1886-1891 Studied at the University of Edinburgh, received M.A.
1891 Immigrated with family to Canada
1891-1895 Resident English Master, Upper Canada College, Toronto
1895-1898 Graduate work in English, Harvard University, M.A. (1897), Ph.D. (1898)
1898-1901 Associate Professor of English Literature, Bryn Mawr College
1901-1904 Instructor of English, Harvard University
1904-1906 Professor of English, Columbia University
1905 Became American citizen
1906-1917 Professor of English, Harvard University
1906 Married Elisabeth Muser in Offenburg, Germany, June 25
1914-1915 Exchange Professor, University of Paris
1917-1939 President of Smith College
1920-1946 Trustee, Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Education Served intermittently on the College Entrance Examination Board
1921 Initiated Special Honors program at Smith College
1924 President, Modern Language Association
1924-1945 Editorial Board of G.C. Merriam and Company
1925 Started Junior Year Abroad program at Smith College
1926-1946 Advisory Council, the Open Road, Inc.
1930-1946 Board of Directors, National Association for the Advancement of Colored People
1940-1941 Board of Directors, National Refugee Service
1940-1945 Chair, Executive Committee, Commission to Study the Organization of Peace
1941 Presided over the International Student Service Summer Student Leadership Institute at Campobello, New Brunswick
1942 Board of Overseers, Harvard University
1943 Chair,
1946 Died in Northampton, Massachusetts, February 13
Scope and Contents
The William Allan Neilson Papers consist of 25 linear feet of correspondence, newspaper clippings, manuscripts, press releases, lecture notes, texts of speeches, photographs, and miscellaneous papers which document Neilson's life and career. While these papers contain material dating from Neilson's years at Smith College (1917-1939), his official correspondence as president of the college is stored separately in the College Archives' holdings of records of the Office of the President.
The papers document Neilson's personal life with extensive family material. His letters to his brother and sisters are particularly valuable. Among other things these letters present Neilson's view of life at Bryn Mawr College under M. Carey Thomas, his strong opinions on world politics, his experiences tutoring Helen Keller at Radcliffe College, and his first impressions of Smith College. This series of letters is especially strong for the years between Neilson's arrival at Harvard University for graduate study in 1895 and his marriage in 1905. In addition to the Neilson family correspondence there is extensive correspondence between the Neilson and Muser families plus diaries and writings of Elisabeth Muser Neilson, her parents, and her sister. Much of the Muser family material is in German.
Other personal material such as photographs, correspondence, class notes, and student essays document Neilson's youth and education. His love of his native Scotland and his study of its language and literature are clearly in evidence in his University of Edinburgh essays.
Correspondence and miscellaneous papers, 1917-1946, document such day-to-day concerns as finances, family health, the running of the household, and travel arrangements.
Neilson's career as professor and scholar of English and Scottish literature is represented by class notes and correspondence with students and colleagues which date primarily from his years at Harvard and Radcliffe. Smith College material includes a few notes for courses Neilson taught in the English department but consists primarily of documentation of the events and celebrations of his presidency such as his appointment, inauguration, tenth and twentieth anniversaries, and retirement. Other material documents Neilson's affiliation with scholarly organizations such as the Modern Language Association, the Scottish Text Society, and the Shakespeare Association of America. There are also texts and notes for speeches on Shakespeare and Burns. Neilson's scholarly publications are represented by a number of articles, an unfinished manuscript for a book on allegory, and proofs for a 1942 edition of Shakespeare's plays and poems. Correspondence and news clippings document other writing and editorial projects in different stages of the work. Two such projects of particular interest are the 'five foot shelf' series of Harvard Classics, which Neilson edited with Charles W. Eliot, and the second edition of Webster's New International Dictionary, for which Neilson was editor-in-chief.
In addition to his work as professor, administrator, and scholar, Neilson was much in demand for committee work. As a respected educator and administrator, his advice and support was continually sought by educational institutions and organizations. Correspondence documents Neilson's work as a member of various committees for Harvard University, his suggestions on the planning of the campus and curriculum of Bennington College, and his advice and endorsements for the New School for Social Research and a variety of organizations promoting adult education such as the Affiliated Schools for Workers, the Eliot Foundation for Adult Education, and the Committee on University Extension in the Connecticut Valley.
Neilson was also well-known for his vigorous support of liberal causes of the day. His political activities are reflected in his involvement with a large number of organizations most of which worked for civil liberties, peace, aid to refugees, or improved foreign relations. This work is documented by correspondence with such organizations as the American Civil Liberties Union, the Foreign Policy Association, the American Society for Cultural Relations with Russia, the National Refugee Service, various League of Nations organizations, and the Commission to Study the Organization of Peace.
All of Neilson's interests and concerns are in evidence in his speeches and writings. Texts contained in the papers are a rich source for the study of life at Smith College, and trends in education and politics during Neilson's term as president of Smith (1917-1939). News clippings document the quite considerable attention paid to his views.
Neilson was a renowned speaker who seldom prepared a text, preferring to talk from cursory notes made shortly before the speech was to be delivered. Because of this process the texts contained in the papers are almost exclusively transcriptions. Some of them were edited for publication, others remain more or less as they were delivered. The papers also contain some of Neilson's handwritten notes for speeches.
Correspondence, citations, and news clippings document Neilson's many awards and honors and a group of biographical articles gives an overview of Neilson's life and work. The papers also contain notes, typescripts, and correspondence for Margaret Farrand Thorp's 1956 biography Nelson of Smith.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into six series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Photographs and Portraits
III. Academic Life
IV. Other Activities
V. Speeches
VI. Writings
Additional Formats
Images from this collection are also available online as part of the Five College Archives Digital Access Project.
Related Material
His official correspondence as president of Smith College is stored separately in the College Archives' holdings of records of the Office of the President.
Conditions Governing Access
The William Allan Neilson Papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Most of the material which makes up the William Allan Neilson Personal Papers was located and gathered between 1951 and 1956 by Margaret Farrand Thorp when she was researching and writing her 1956 biography Neilson of Smith. Reminiscences and materials were solicited from family, friends, colleagues, and students. Other materials were discovered in various storerooms on campus. There is little specific information about when or how but most of this material eventually found its way to the College Archives.
Bibliography
Selected Bibliography: Editorial Projects: For a more complete biographical sketch see the Dictionary of American Biography Supplement 1946-1950.
The Origins and Sources of the Court of Love (1899)
The Essentials of Poetry (1912)
The Facts about Shakespeare (1913)
Robert Burns: How to Know Him (1917)
Harvard Classics "Five Foot Shelf" (1909-1910)
Cambridge Shakespeare (1906, revised 1942)
Webster's New International Dictionary, 2nd Ed. (1934)
Neilson, William Allan, 1869-1946.; Neilson, Elisabeth Muser, 1882-1968.; Smith College--Presidents.; Harvard University--Faculty.; Radcliffe College--Faculty.; Thorp, Margaret Farrand, 1891-; Smith College. Office of President.
- Series I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL, 1852-1982; 8 linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series is divided into four sections: 'General;' 'Education;' 'Family;' and 'Writings About Neilson.'
  'General' consists of correspondence, news clippings, award certificates and citations, memorabilia, and miscellaneous notes pertaining to Neilson's life, career, and death. The material in this section is arranged by subject with the oversize material in a separate sequence.
  'Education' consists of essays, notes, and miscellaneous papers primarily from his years at the University of Edinburgh and at Harvard University. There are two notebooks and an article which pre-date Neilson's college days. This material is arranged chronologically with the oversize material in a separate sequence.
  'Family' consists primarily of correspondence with some writings and diaries. Both the Neilson and Muser families are well represented. The material is arranged by family and then alphabetically by individual with oversize material in a separate sequence.
  'Writings About Neilson' contains biographical articles and volumes arranged in two sequences alphabetically by title.
  - General
    - Newspaper clippings, 1873-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Biographical sketches, 1917-1941; undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Chronology, 1869-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Genealogy, 1927-1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Awards
      - Miscellaneous; news clippings, awards, programs, 1913-1941; undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Honorary degrees, miscellaneous: citations, news clippings, correspondence, awards, 1918-1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Edinburgh, University of: award, correspondence, news clippings, press release, citation, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Foreign Policy Association: award, news clippings, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - France, Legion of Honor: correspondence, news clippings, press releases, program, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Harvard University: correspondence, news clippings, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Kenyon College: citation, correspondence, news clippings, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - McGill University: citation, correspondence, news clippings, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Mt. Holyoke College: citation, correspondence, news clippings, honorary degree, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - National Institute of Immigrant Welfare: speech by James G. MacDonald, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Oberlin College: citation, correspondence, news clippings, honorary degree, photographs, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Princeton University: correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Probus Club: award, correspondence, news clippings, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Smith College anniversary, tributes and honorary degree: citation, news clippings, 1927; 1937; 1942 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Spain, Order of Alfonso VII: award, citation, news clippings, press releases, photograph, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Yale University: citation, correspondence, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, miscellaneous, 1907-1941; undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Death
      - Burial certificate, correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Memorial service: news clippings, notes, 1946 February 16 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Obituaries: press releases, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Obituaries: news clippings, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Tributes, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Finances: bills, correspondence, 1918-1939 (Box 1, Folder 27-37)
    - Health: correspondence, charts, 1929-1939 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Houses
      - Cambridge, 34 Kirkland Street: correspondence, 1917-1921 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Maine: correspondence, 1919-1928 (Box 2, Folder 40-41)
      - Retirement: correspondence, 1939; June-July (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Household
      - General and miscellaneous: correspondence, 1919-1939 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      - Cecile de Saint-Paul: correspondence, 1919-1921 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      - Elfriede Schneller: correspondence, 1925-1935 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - Irmgard Zoeppritz: correspondence, 1924-1934 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Insurance: certificates, correspondence, pamphlets, 1890-1939 (Box 2, Folder 47-51)
    - Miscellany
      - Article on J.M. Barrie not written by WAN, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - Clippings, notes, and poems from "Commonplace Book", 1900 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - Offenburg notes, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Purchases: bills, correspondence, receipts, 1918-1939 (Box 2, Folder 55-58)
    - Travel arrangements: correspondence, passenger lists, 1894; 1921-1939 (Box 2, Folder 59-60)
    - Travel arrangements: passports, 1915-1935 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Education
    - Montrose Academy: "The Athletic Sports" (article for school magazine), 1886 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Notes on Greek literature, 1884 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Notes on Greek poetry, 1886 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - University of Edinburgh
      - Miscellaneous, 1886-1891 (Box 3, Folder 65)
        General
        [See also Box 13]
      - Certificates and diploma, 1886-1891 (Box 3, Folder 66)
      - Letter of recommendation, 1890-1891 (Box 3, Folder 67)
      - Essay, "The Basis of Private Property", 1889 (Box 3, Folder 68)
      - Essay, "The Comparison of Ancient and Modern Ethics, Taking as the Test the Cardinal Virtues of the Ancient Philosophy and the Catergorical Imperative of the Modern", 1891 (Box 3, Folder 69)
      - Essay, "Conscience", 1889-1890 (Box 3, Folder 70)
      - Essay, "Free Will", 1889-1890 (Box 3, Folder 71)
      - Essay, "Nationality in Literature" (competition essay), 1890 (Box 3, Folder 72)
      - Essay, "On the Consistency and Inconsistency of the 4th Book of Locke's 'Essay' with the Other 3 Books…", 1890-1891 (Box 3, Folder 73)
      - Essay, "The Place of Synthesis in Philosophy", 1889-1890 (Box 3, Folder 74)
      - Essay, "A Saturday Evening in Edinburgh", 1889 (Box 3, Folder 75)
      - Essay, "Scottish Place Names and Their Origin", 1888 (Box 3, Folder 76)
      - Essay, "Sense Perception and the Various Explanations of It", 1889 (Box 3, Folder 77)
      - Essay, "Shakespeare's Ariel", 1890 (Box 3, Folder 78)
      - Essay, "The Study of Mind as Means of Culture", 1888 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Class notes (Box 3)
      [See Box 14]
    - Harvard University
      - Miscellaneous: correspondence, grades, scholarship notification, 1895-98 (Box 3, Folder 80)
      - Notes on Keats and Spenser, undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
      - Essay, "Character Drawing in Waverly Novels", 1896 (Box 3, Folder 82)
      - Essay, "Poets' Theories of Poetry", 1896-1897 (Box 3, Folder 83)
      - Essay, "Report on an Investigation into the Attitude of the People of Scotland towards the Church…", 1894? (Box 3, Folder 84)
      - Notebook, "19th century prose," Mr. Gates, 1895-1896 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Family
    - Miscellaneous, 1859-1891 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Allan, William (uncle): correspondence, memorial tributes, 1872-1873; 1928; undated (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Allan, Mary (cousin): correspondence, 1921-1939 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Burgess, David and Jim (cousin and nephew): correspondence, 1926-1933 (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Burgess, J. (uncle): correspondence to Doune Sabbath School from Calcutta, 1856 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Neilson, Allan von Poetz (son): correspondence, news clippings, 1921-1925 (Box 4, Folder 90-91)
    - Neilson, Caroline Louise (daughter): correspondence, news clippings, 1925-1941 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Neilson, David (father): miscellaneous papers, 1851-1870; undated (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Neilson, David (father): correspondence, 1850-1881; undated (Box 4, Folder 94-96)
    - Neilson, David (father): essays by students, undated (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Neilson, David (father): school address and songs, undated (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Neilson, Elizabeth (sister): correspondence, 1897-1917; undated (Box 4, Folder 99-100)
    - Neilson, Jean Armor (sister): miscellaneous, 1905-1939 (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Neilson, Jean Armor (sister): correspondence from WAN, 1897-1942 (Box 4, Folder 102-107)
    - Neilson, Margaret (daughter): correspondence, news clippings, early memories, 1931-1942 (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - Neilson, Mary Allan (mother): correspondence, 1856-1868; undated (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - Neilson, Mary Allan (mother): correspondence with David Neilson (father), 1859-1873; undated (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - Neilson, Mary Allan (mother): correspondence from WAN and Robert Neilson (brother), 1885; 1897; undated (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Robert Neilson (brother): miscellaneous, 1902-34; undated (Box 5, Folder 112)
    - Robert Neilson (brother): correspondence from David Neilson (father), 1876 (Box 5, Folder 113)
    - Robert Neilson (brother): correspondence from WAN, 1893-1905 June (Box 5, Folder 114-120)
    - Robert Neilson (brother): correspondence from WAN and Elisabeth Muser Neilson, 1905 July-1933; undated (Box 5, Folder 121-132)
    - Elisabeth Muser Neilson (wife)
      - Correspondence, miscellaneous, 1899-1967; undated (Box 6, Folder 133-34)
      - Correspondence from Else Gerner, 1899-1907; undated (Box 6, Folder 135-38)
      - Correspondence with Emil Gott, 1900-1908; undated (Box 6, Folder 139-42)
      - Correspondence from Manding Harlacher (her cousin), 1899-1928; undated (Box 6, Folder 143-47)
      - Correspondence from Max Harrer, 1903-1906 (Box 6, Folder 148-49)
      - Correspondence with Margarete Muser (her sister), 1899-1909; undated (Box 6, Folder 150-51)
      - Correspondence to WAN, 1904-1905 (Box 6, Folder 152)
      - Correspondence with Amalie von Poetz (her aunt), 1900-1939 (Box 6, Folder 153-56)
      - Correspondence from Mina von Poetz (her cousin), 1920-1926 (Box 6, Folder 157)
      - Correspondence with Lina and Oskar Muser (her parents), 1899-1915 (Box 7, Folder 158-179)
      - Correspondence with Lina and Oskar Muser (her parents), 1916-1938 (Box 8, Folder 180-197)
      - Correspondence with Lina Kuser (her mother), 1938-1941; undated (Box 8, Folder 198-201)
      - School notebooks, 1895-1899 (Box 9)
      - Postcard album, undated (Box 9)
      - News clipping scrapbook, undated (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous, 1900; 1939; undated (Box 10, Folder 202)
      - News clippings, 1939-1968 (Box 10, Folder 203)
      - Miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 10, Folder 204)
      - Children's play- (Box 10, Folder 205)
      - "Space and Time in Rainer Maria Rilke's Poetry", 1947 (Box 10, Folder 206)
      - Essay, "Space and Time in Rainer Maria Rilke's Poetry": correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 10, Folder 207)
      - Essay, "The Metaphysical Implications of Rilke's Book of Hours" (early version of article above), undated (Box 10, Folder 208)
      - Essay, "Raum und Zeit in Rilke's Dichtung" (German version), undated (Box 10, Folder 209)
      - Poems, 1921? (Box 10, Folder 210)
    - Lina Huser (mother-in-law)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1908-1941 (Box 10, Folder 211)
      - Correspondence to her family, 1876-1909; undated (Box 10, Folder 212-13)
      - Correspondence from Emil Gott, 1899-1903; undated (Box 10, Folder 214-15)
      - Correspondence with Margarete Muser (her daughter), 1901-1909; undated (Box 10, Folder 216)
      - Correspondence with Amalie von Poetz (her sister), 1877-1939; undated (Box 10, Folder 217)
      - Poems, 1900-1901 (Box 10, Folder 218)
    - Lina and Oskar Muser (parents-in-law)
      - Miscellaneous, 1885-1891; 1915-1937; undated (Box 10, Folder 219)
      - Correspondence to Allan, Caroline, and Margaret Neilson, 1915-1941 (Box 10, Folder 220)
      - Correspondence with WAN and Elizabeth Muser Neilson, 1907-1934 (Box 10, Folder 221)
      - Correspondence from Helene Tafel, 1899-1903 (Box 10, Folder 222)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1878-1905; undated (Box 10, Folder 223-24)
    - Oskar Muser; account of the last few days of his life by ?, 1938 (Box 10, Folder 225)
    - Lina and Margarete Muser: correspondence to WAN, 1908-1936 (Box 10, Folder 226)
    - Margarete Muser: miscellaneous correspondence, 1904-1914; undated (Box 10, Folder 227)
    - Margarete Muser: correspondence with Else Gerner, 1901-1910; undated (Box 10, Folder 228)
  - Writings About Neilson
    - "Neilson of Smith" by Hubert Herring, Harper's Magazine, 1938 June (Box 11, Folder 229)
    - Neilson of Smith by Hubert Herring (bound version), 1939 (Box 11, Folder 230)
    - "Neilson of Smith" by Marjorie Hope Nicolson, The American Scholar, 1946 Autumn (Box 11, Folder 231)